<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Practical Executive</title>
    <description>How to take your small business to the next level through data driven insights and experience forged expertise.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 22:30:19 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 22:30:19 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Want To Lose Half Your Savings? Then Diversify!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“What! How can something which is specifically meant to lower the risk of me losing my life savings - cause me to lose my life savings!?” Let me show you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not doing something with your savings besides hoarding it in a bank, then STOP reading right now and &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#109;&amp;#101;&amp;#064;&amp;#106;&amp;#111;&amp;#115;&amp;#104;&amp;#117;&amp;#097;&amp;#115;&amp;#099;&amp;#104;&amp;#117;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#122;&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt;, I &lt;strong&gt;have to show&lt;/strong&gt; you how leaving your money in the bank is costing you 2% - 5% every single year! That’s right, you are &lt;em&gt;losing&lt;/em&gt; that every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you already have some type of savings plan or investments, then read on! I am going to show you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why you must diversify&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why the way everyone shows you is extremely dangerous to your &lt;em&gt;wealth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problems with this dated way of thinking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The devastating result of doing the way financial advisors and books are showing you (and it’s not pretty)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new framework to use which is identical to the exact methods used by one of the best money managers in world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An exact step-by-step method to implement this in your savings starting today&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A way to look smarter next time your friends and co-workers are talking about their investments!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-diversification&quot;&gt;What is diversification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very plainly, diversification is scattering your money in all different areas for the purpose of lowering your risk of losing money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are close to 100 different &lt;em&gt;risks&lt;/em&gt; when investing, but let’s consider just two for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is the risk that you are most concerned with when building savings for early retirement, or perhaps that upcoming vacation, the risk of losing money!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The other risk that we will consider for the current moment is that of something going wrong with a specific investment, also known as &lt;em&gt;unsystematic risk&lt;/em&gt;. That is a fancy word for “What if the company loses money, or goes bankrupt, or doesn’t get that FDA approval on a new drug?” It just refers to something bad happening to only one company, not the entire economy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s say you have all your money in a nice safe corporate bond. Perhaps you don’t trust the stock market and you prefer the safe feeling of getting those bond payments every 6 months direct deposited into your bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/bond.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Safe Corporate Bond&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are really smart, so you buy the bonds of a &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt; company such as &lt;strong&gt;IBM&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;INTEL&lt;/strong&gt;. What happens if over time there are new companies founded, and they challenge these existing giants, taking business away from them? Or worse yet, what if another moment of economic hardship hits like 2008 and your Bond Issuer’s (IBM in this case) financial situation changes? Well, just like with you when your money gets tight, some bills don’t get paid - and for them, you are one of the lowest bills on their priority list. Even though you had a &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt; investment, you still could &lt;strong&gt;lose everything&lt;/strong&gt;. This is because you &lt;em&gt;put all your money into one investment&lt;/em&gt; and experienced that risk we called &lt;em&gt;unsystematic risk&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wise men of diversification say “Well, you need to buy all different types of bonds so that if one of them has a problem, you don’t lose all your money!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-diversify&quot;&gt;Why diversify&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the common reason stated for diversification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is to prevent one bad event at some company somewhere from completely wiping out your savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you put all your money into the pot one just hand of poker (if you said yes, this information just isn’t for you)? Of course not! You spread the &lt;em&gt;risk&lt;/em&gt; around in case you have a few bad hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I am going to show you in this article is how to make your portfolio so that it would take many negative events to take away your savings. In a following article, I am actually going to show you &lt;strong&gt;how to make your account grow even as negative events occur&lt;/strong&gt;! That’s right, the second step to implementing this strategy is that while everyone else’s savings and wealth goes down, yours actually goes up! But to really understand this, I need to first show you why traditional diversification isn’t what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diversification-doesnt-actually-exist&quot;&gt;Diversification doesn’t actually exist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diversification logic sounds great, but it doesn’t actually work in real life. There is something that many don’t seem to realize when they give you this advice. You go to financial advisors and they throw these buzz words at you, but are they really helping you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me show you a quick chart which will really drive this this point home, then I’ll show you how following this advice blindly would have lost up to half of everything you had saved had you done this over the last 3 - 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-math-behind-diversification&quot;&gt;The math behind diversification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diversification is based on the simple idea that if all my money or &lt;em&gt;risk&lt;/em&gt; is in one place, then my entire savings account - which is hard to replace - can be wiped out by one negative event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;chart1div&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the above assumption, the experts tell you that by adding other investments, you lower risk. If you think about it in a simple straight forward manner, the more investments you add, the lower your overall risk. If you have 40 different investments in stocks, and one of the companies goes bankrupt, you still have 39 investments growing… you will barely even feel it! So the amount of &lt;em&gt;risk&lt;/em&gt; your portfolio has decreased in proportion to how many stocks you have in your portfolio. Sounds great, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-end-result-of-diversification&quot;&gt;The end result of diversification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there are two problems with this (actually there are more, but we’ll just cover two).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-1-with-diversification&quot;&gt;Problem 1 With Diversification&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are investing to grow your savings. Talk to 30 people you know, and look at their actual investment returns (as opposed to the imaginary returns they brag about). Then average all of these returns. My guess is you will probably come out right about 0%. Yup! That’s right, some make money, some lose money, but the average probably net right around 0%. Now look back at our idea from the last section. What happens if you keep adding more and more stocks to your portfolio? Won’t your portfolio returns approach average? You’ll get some great winners and some nasty losers, but your average return will be mediocre at best. How could it not, you took every stock and just mixed it together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-2-with-diversification&quot;&gt;Problem 2 With Diversification&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more important problem is the definition of risk that all of the advisors and so called experts are focusing on! They are only looking at unsystematic risk (or the risk of a negative corporate event impacting your portfolio in a negative way). Remember I told you that there are many many risks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s play out a scenario. What are some reasons a company might have a hard time growing its earnings or paying its bills?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sales are down and people aren’t buying as much?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The banks aren’t lending and its hard to get the cash need to run the business?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The materials they buy to build their product or deliver their service are increasing in price, so their costs are going up and their margins down?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at each of those, are there times when this happens to many companies &lt;strong&gt;at the same time&lt;/strong&gt;? Absolutely, it happens all the time! Can you predict the next risk I am going to introduce you to? What if the same problem that causes the 40th company in your nice safe portfolio to decline in price, also causes the other 39 companies to decline in price? Now we have a problem! This is &lt;em&gt;systematic&lt;/em&gt; risk, or risk that effects all the companies. Diversification didn’t help you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-illusion-of-diversification&quot;&gt;The illusion of diversification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We generally call these times a &lt;em&gt;Recession&lt;/em&gt;, when all businesses have a hard time. Recessions cause or experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;less consumer buying because people are nervous about their jobs or their incomes are lower&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;businesses not investing or growing because there is no more easy credit from the banks like before&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;materials can get really expensive (remember how much oil went up in 2008?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that your portfolio will not receive the benefits that were desired as you placed 40 different investments in your portfolio. Yikes! At the very moment you needed diversification most, it left you high and dry and vanished!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wall Street has a saying…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In difficult times, all correlations go to 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meaning - when things get tough, everything goes down together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So not only did you get &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; returns at best on the upside, you participate fulling in the downside. If you are my friend, please don’t diversify like this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-practice-of-diversification&quot;&gt;The practice of diversification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular methods for diversification by the average guy and gal are mutual funds, a so called diversified portfolio of stocks assembled for you, by someone who knows more than you. Right? Let’s take a brief but closer look at these mutual funds and what they contain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Funds is one of the biggest companies that has mutual funds used in retirement account and other savings plans. Below I have shown you the top 10 stocks in their &lt;em&gt;Growth Fund&lt;/em&gt; along side another mutual fund run by &lt;em&gt;MFS&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;large-6 columns&quot; id=&quot;chart2div&quot; style=&quot;width:50%;height:500px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;large-6 columns&quot; id=&quot;chart3div&quot; style=&quot;width:50%;height:500px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything look similiar? If you begin to look at many of the top funds, you will see that they all hold roughly the same companies. One of the reasons this occurs is because of fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The managers running these mutual funds don’t want to look &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; different, so they stay with &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt; stocks. Essentially the same ones everyone else uses. This way, if something goes wrong, at least everybody experienced it too. It is to safeguard their reputation, not to help your returns. If they made some unique investment choices which turned sour, many people would leave the fund. Trust me, their marketing department doesn’t want this to happen! So it is better to be &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens if there is now a recession, and many of these mutual funds need to either&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sell stocks to raise cash because investors need this money back due to hardship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sell stocks because of poor performance in price?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the stocks get sold at the same time, by the funds who all own the same stocks! So your “diversified” basket of stocks was in reality a mirage of diversity for fund managers to show their different types of companies owned&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-this-thinking-is-all-wrong&quot;&gt;Why This Thinking is All Wrong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what have we learned so far?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversification is suppose to lower the risk of you losing money by spreading around your money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversification, in theory, is a good idea. It works for company specific risk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversification doesn’t take into effect the fact that when things get rough, all the stocks go down together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most popular vehicles used for diversification, aren’t really diversified at all!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we need is an idea, which lower our risk, but does so when we need it most! Well guess what, I have just the idea for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-need-to-diversify-risk-not-returns&quot;&gt;We need to diversify Risk, not returns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we need to do is understand what we are trying to diversify. In your savings account, what you &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; want is to &lt;strong&gt;not lose money&lt;/strong&gt;! To do this, we should look at all the different risks, and make sure that no single risk can take away our entire portfolio!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, I am going to ask you to think differently than financial advisors, CNBC pundits, and the sweet talking newsletter writers. Let’s consider what it is we &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; want, and then get it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to not lose money, we need to diversify &lt;strong&gt;risks&lt;/strong&gt;. That is, rather than picking a bunch of stocks which will all go down when we face systematic risk (risk that effects all stocks), we should pick a bunch of investments (be open minded here) that will go up no matter what the shock or environment is. We are choosing many different investments, not just stocks and bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-new-framework-for-the-practical-millennial&quot;&gt;A new framework for the practical millennial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you understand the problem with traditional diversification, and you are ready to take charge with your savings. You know what not to do, what about the other half?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main aspects of our economy that matter at any time. The amount of economic activity, and the price of that activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;economic-environments&quot;&gt;Economic Environments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the good old days when everyone had a job, raises were every year, and no-one heard the term “budget cuts?” That is what we call economic growth, and its a fun time to be alive. The opposite isn’t so fun. That is when we have a hard time finding jobs, and its hard to get by. These not so happy times, and the rate of employment all fall under the umbrella of economic &lt;strong&gt;Growth&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand we have the current price of the this growth. Pricing can go up or down, regardless on whether the economy is growing or now. For example, remember 2008? Would you say there was economic growth? Probably not, so there was economic decline occurring there. Yet, do you remember gas prices and oil… &lt;em&gt;skyrocketing&lt;/em&gt;. The price of goods was going up even though our growth was non-extent. This second economic aspect we’ll call &lt;strong&gt;Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at anytime, we have some combination of the following:
* Economic growth
* Economic decline
* Inflation
* Deflation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;risk-parity&quot;&gt;Risk Parity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know this, but the problem is, we never know which one is coming. So what do we do? We &lt;strong&gt;Diversify&lt;/strong&gt; Haha, you knew it was coming. We don’t buy a bunch of stocks, we buy different investments, each one will do really really well in &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; of the economic environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we don’t need to forecast, we don’t need to be financial geniuses, and we don’t need to always worry. Once we implement this strategy, we can rest knowing that know matter what, at least 50% of our portfolio will be benefiting from the current economic environment. PHEW!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diversify-risk-not-assets&quot;&gt;Diversify Risk not Assets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one little detail I still need to share with you… &lt;strong&gt;do not put 25% of your assets into each one of these investments!&lt;/strong&gt; That is the incorrect methodology that your financial advisor will tell you. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, every asset &lt;em&gt;moves&lt;/em&gt; differently. Stocks move a lot. They may go up 5% one week and down 3.5% the next. Compare this to government treasures for the United States. On a great week they may increase by 1% - 2%. The amount of movement that occurs with an asset is called &lt;strong&gt;Volatility&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we put $50,000 into stocks, and $50,000 into government treasuries. We tried to &lt;em&gt;diversify&lt;/em&gt;. We then have a bad week.
* The stocks in our portfolio will go down 5% and so they will lose 5% x $50,000 or $2,500 in one week.
* The bonds in our portfolio will go down 2% and so they will lose $50,000 x 2% or $1,000 in one week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though we divided our portfolio into two equal parts, the stock portion lost more than 2x the amount the bond portion lost! Why? Because the stocks move more, or they have &lt;em&gt;higher volatility&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in order to correctly diversify our portfolio, we need to make the risk equal, not the amount invested. Imagine instead if we had a portfolio invested as like this:
* Portfolio is $100,000 like above
* We have $28,500 in stocks
* We have $71,500 in bonds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what happens when we encounter that bad week?
* Stocks will lose 5% x $28,500 or $1425
* Bonds will lose 2% x $71,500 or $1430&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost the same! Now &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; is a balanced portfolio. Now combining this method of choosing how much of each investment to buy, combined with buying assets that do well in &lt;strong&gt;each&lt;/strong&gt; of the economic environments gives you a well protected portfolio that can do well under any economic condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-new-portfolio&quot;&gt;Your new portfolio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in the exact specifics, just click here and I’ll send you for free, a detailed sheet
* outlining the exact investments to use
* where to get them
* exactly how much of each one you need to buy
* and the step by step process I use to implement this in my own portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to help you with your finances any way I can. If there is a frustration or question you have regarding personal finance or investments, I would &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; to hear it! Send me an email or tweet, I answer every single one personally.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 08:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>/wealth/2016/02/01/how-diversification-leads-to-losing-your-savings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/wealth/2016/02/01/how-diversification-leads-to-losing-your-savings.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>wealth</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
