<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Practical Executive</title>
    <description>How to take your small business to the next level through data driven insights and experience forged expertise.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 15:06:28 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 15:06:28 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Small Business Can Save The World!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Each day, as you make your morning cup of coffee you play the news, curious as to what may have happened in the last 24 hours. Perhaps a quick scroll of twitter gives you all the information you need, or perhaps you like to glance over the first few pages of the Journal on the train heading to work. &lt;strong&gt;And there it is&lt;/strong&gt;, more bad news, negative situations, and overall gloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/bad_news.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fear Sells, unfortunately&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we know that &lt;em&gt;fear sells&lt;/em&gt;, and that good news is vastly under reported, this story you are reading still occured… There still exists these daily reminders that all is not well. Perhaps it is another story on the “1%” lining their pockets with cashed-out stock options while their employees are forced towards unemployment, or perhaps it’s an account of the 3rd suicide off the local bridge because a young man couldn’t see a way out of his depressed life… These injustices exist, and it seems we are powerless to help. So what can small business do for this you may ask? Read on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;chartdiv&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-you-personally-can-still-have-an-impact&quot;&gt;Why you personally can still have an impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There is nothing new under the sun” - Solomon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of this world lies human beings - You and me! Behind the algorthims that push our markets lies the creator of the theoroms and engineer of the code. &lt;em&gt;Behind much of the automatic, and seemingly overpowering world we live in, lies people just like you&lt;/em&gt;! They have dreams to travel and see remote places, an itch to create and share some message with the world just like you, something they feel they can offer to a group of people - no matter how big or small - just like you feel right now! However, they have found a way to reach out and grab those dreams and make them a reality! Their successive dreams are then more ambitous and their newly attained resolve is now more powerful. They are building momentum in accomplishment while the rest of us are wondering what happened to the last 10 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many problems that we see, and we turn these problems in the reasons not to be our true selves rather than to use them as a platform for revealing who we are and what we have to offer. Perhaps you love the movement and grace of dance and want a way to share that with your city, well I know my life needs more grace! Or maybe you are excellent with increasing the conversion of cold calls for distribution facilities - I NEED to hear from you! You see… and pay attention to this point… ** Every single person has something that this world NEEDS**, and by not releasing it, you are blocking a fulfilled life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exponential-effects-of-one-change-in-an-ecosystem&quot;&gt;Exponential effects of one change in an ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This entire world is an ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt;. Do you know the amazing thing about ecosystems? &lt;em&gt;As each part begins to do their role and function in the greater whole, there are exponential results in the rest of the system!&lt;/em&gt; Let me give you an example. George Monbiot found one small ecosystem in North America and made ONE SMALL seemingly INSIGNIFICANT change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know what that was?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He re-introduced wolves into Yellowstone Park. What do you think happened? After more than 70 years without wolves, Yellowstone had found an equilibrium of existance without them - the the parks potential if this one animal were where it should be, when it should be there, was &lt;strong&gt;hidden&lt;/strong&gt;! After George started re-introducing the wolves back into the Yellowstone ecosystem, an avalanche of changes occured. &lt;strong&gt;Many of these changes could not have been predicted and seem completely unrelated.&lt;/strong&gt; Check this out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Packs of wolves altered the deer paths&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deer feeding in different areas and their movement changes caused vegetation to change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new vegetation structure attracted new animals which had not previously existed in the park including beavers, eagles, bears, and rabbits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These new animals built natural infrastructure which actually changed the course of the river!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you believe that! Wolves changed the course of an entire river!&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t believe me? Listen to George tell you himself&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/8rZzHkpyPkc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see his quicker talk on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ysa5OBhXz-Q&quot;&gt;youtube&lt;/a&gt;. Do you see where I am going with this? Are you getting excited?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine one person making a change. &lt;strong&gt;Now imagine that change affected income dispersion, suicide rates, and even your own fulfillment.&lt;/strong&gt; Now imagine more and more of these changes occuring and the way it would change our ecosystem which we all live in everyday! How is this possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-business-is-the-answer&quot;&gt;Small Business is the answer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By starting, working for, or supporting small business, the ecosystem we call the “economy”, and all of its moving pieces can have massive changes on our lives, our nation, and our world. See below some of the major benefits of increased small business, and why I have dedicated my life to helping build, grow, and optimize them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is better to have 100 companies of 10 people,
than 1 company of 1000!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decentralized production&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased consumer choice &amp;amp; differentiation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Natural risk dispersion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased economic demand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased country wealth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automatic income redistribution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specialization of supply&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased quality of production and service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased personal fulfillment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhanced individual and corporate creativity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better customer service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be highlighting these over the coming weeks with specific examples of why we need small businesses to succeed. If you have a small business or a small business idea, I would love to hear your thoughts! &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#109;&amp;#101;&amp;#064;&amp;#106;&amp;#111;&amp;#115;&amp;#104;&amp;#117;&amp;#097;&amp;#115;&amp;#099;&amp;#104;&amp;#117;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#122;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;Send me a message&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/joshuamschultz&quot;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt; on twitter and let me know other benefits of small business, and more importantly, &lt;strong&gt;what I can do to help you grow your business&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 08:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>/purpose/2016/01/21/how-small-business-will-save-the-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/purpose/2016/01/21/how-small-business-will-save-the-world.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>purpose</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
